Finding Aid for Solomon Jacob Axelrod papers, 1934-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Academic Materials
  - Course Planning, 1956-1967
    - Other Courses, 1961-1967 (Box 10)
  - Department of Medical Care Organization-History, 1984 (Box 10)
  - Doctor of Public Health, 1965-1968 (Box 10)
  - Epidemiology, 1941-1949
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 10)
    - Lecture Notes, 1949 (Box 10)
    - Lecture Notes-University of Pennsylvania, 1941 (Box 10)
    - Seminars and Problems, undated; 1948 (Box 10)
  - Faculty Seminar on Income Maintenance Programs, 1956-1957 (Box 10)
  - Lecture Materials, 1952-1983
    - Aging, 1950; 1954; 1960-1962; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Background Factors, undated; 1974-1980 (Box 10)
    - Benefits, undated; 1973; 1977 (Box 10)
    - Costs and Expenditures, 1967-1979 (Box 11)
      - Containment, undated; 1968-1979 (Box 11)
      - General and Total Expenditures, undated; 1972-1979 (Box 11)
    - Rising Costs, undated; 1967-1974 (Box 11)
    - Environmental Sanitation, undated (Box 11)
    - Group Practice, undated; 1965-1975 (Box 11)
    - Health Insurance, 1952-1978
      - Benefits, undated; 1964-1979 (Box 11)
      - Coverage, undated; 1954; 1972-1978 (Box 11)
      - General, undated; 1965-1973 (Box 11)
      - Major Medical and Commercial, undated; 1954; 1962 (Box 11)
      - Prepaid Plans and Others, undated; 1952-1971 (Box 11)
      - Principles, History, and Classification, undated; 1974-1978 (Box 11)
      - Private and Mental Health, undated, 1970-1973 (Box 11)
    - Health Maintenance Organizations, undated; 1971-1983 (Box 11)
    - Hospitals, undated; 1971-1978 (Box 11)
    - International Health, 1967 (Box 11)
    - Introductory Lecture (MCO 600), 1974-1975 (Box 11)
    - Manpower, undated; 1945; 1970-1982 (Box 11)
    - Medicaid, undated; 1973-1981 (Box 11)
    - National Health Insurance, 1967-1979
      - Bibliographies and Syllabi, 1970-1975 (Box 11)
      - General, undated; 1967-1972; 1975-1979; 4 folders (Box 11)
      - Historical Development, undated; 1971-1976 (Box 11)
    - National Health Planning & International Assistance, 1963 (Box 12)
    - Need, undated; 1973 (Box 12)
    - Non-Allopathic Medicine 1975, 1981 (Wayne State University Lecture, includes photograph of Homeopathic Drugstore in Merida, Mexico) (Box 12)
    - Organization of Financing, 1963-1978
      - Role of Government, undated; 1963-1978; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Tax Supported Programs, undated; 1968-1978 (Box 12)
    - Organization of Services, undated; 1969-1981; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Overview-MCO 600, 1973-1977 (Box 12)
    - Patterns of Practice, 1961-1974
      - I: MD's, undated; 1963-1974 (Box 12)
      - II: Content and Context, undated; 1961-1972 (Box 12)
    - Public Health Practices and Economics, 1954-1959 (Box 12)
    - Venereal Disease (Box 12)
    - Quality, undated, 1973-1976 (Box 12)
    - Types of Plans-Evaluation, undated; 1969-1977 (Box 12)
  - Master's Degree Program, 1955-1967; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Master's of Public Health-Employment, 1966-1969 (Box 12)
  - Medicare Lecture Materials, 1975-1977 (Box 12)
  - Medicare Talks
    - 1960s, 1970s (Box 12)
    - 1986 (Box 12)
  - Medical Care Teachers (Box 12)
  - Office of Research Administration
    - Executive Committee, 1964 (Box 12)
  - Papers Presented
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Canadian Medical Association, 1956 (Box 12)
  - Proposed Building Program, 1965 (Box 12)
  - School of Public Health
    - Bureau of Public Health Economics
      - Annual Reports, 1959-1966; 5 folders (Box 12)
      - Job Analysis Report, September 1950 (Box 12)
      - Organizational Charts (Box 12)
      - Report: "Three Fiscal Years in Health Economics" (Box 12)
    - Committee on Institute of Hospital Affairs, 1955 (Box 13)
    - Department of Medical Care Organization, 1968-1969 (Box 13)
    - Department of Public Health Practice, 1959-1960 (Box 13)
    - Disease Studies
      - Cerebral Palsy, 1955-1957; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Tuberculosis Evaluation Program, 1955-1956; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Michigan Medical Facilities Survey
      - Budget, 1955-1957 (Box 13)
      - Chronic Disease Facilities, 1954 (Box 13)
      - General, 1957 (Box 13)
      - Haven Hill Conference, 1957 (Box 13)
      - Study Materials, 1956 (Box 13)
      - Study Reports, 1956-1957 (Box 13)
    - Planning Materials, 1967-1969 (Box 13)
    - Research Projects and Proposals
      - Dental, 1955 (Box 13)
      - General, 1949-1961; 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Hospital Beds, 1954-1955 (Box 13)
      - Hospital Utilization, 1960 (Box 13)
      - Manitoba Medical Services, 1955 (Box 13)
      - Michigan Needs and Resources, 1955 (Box 13)
      - Oakland County Nursing Homes, 1952-1955 (Box 13)
      - Occupational Analysis, 1952 (Box 13)
      - Ontario Blue Cross, 1955-1957 (Box 13)
      - Retirement Research (UAW), 1956-1957 (Box 13)
      - Social Science Research Project, 1955 (Box 13)
      - Washington Blue Shield, 1956 (Box 13)
    - Windsor Medical Care Survey
      - General, 1955-1957 (Box 13)
      - Health Insurance Fees, 1954-1957 (Box 13)
      - Monthly Utilization Data, 1955 (Box 13)
      - Population Survey Materials, 1954 (Box 13)
      - Reports, 1952-1954; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Senate Advisory Committee
    - 1957 (Box 13)
    - 1958, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1959, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Advisory Committee to Vice President (Business & Finance), 1964-1965 (Box 13)
    - Subcommittee on Research Policy, 1957-1962; 3 folders (Box 13)
  - University of California at Irvine, 1977-1981
    - Academic Planning Group, 1979 (Box 14)
    - Delivery System, 1979-1980 (Box 14)
    - General, 1979-1980 (Box 14)
    - Health Maintenance Organizations, 1977-1980 (Box 14)
    - Issues, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
    - Kaiser, 1979 (Box 14)
    - Medi-Cal, 1979 (Box 14)
    - Occupational Health Seminar, 1979 (Box 14)
    - Organization of Medical Services, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
    - Student Health Service, 1978-1981 (Box 14)
    - Yale Health Plan, 1977; 1979 (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan
    - Academic Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 14)
    - Black Action Movement / School of Public Health, 1970 (Box 14)
    - "Economic Delivery of Health Services,", 1970 (Box 14)
    - "The Future of the Voluntary Movement,", 1961 (Box 14)
    - "Implications for Public Health Nursing,", 1961 (Box 14)
    - MCO Student Committee, 1970 (Box 14)
    - Review of School of Public Health, 1969 (Box 14)
    - Report on Community Medicine, 1971 (Box 14)
    - "Toward A Comprehensive Community", 1969 (Box 14)
  - Veteran's Administration, 1979-1981 (Box 14)
  - Welcome to Mercaz Kupat Holim Beilinson Hospital, 1962 (Box 14)
  - Unprocessed (incl. Drug Benefits, Coverage) (Box 14)
- Correspondence, 1944-1986
  The Correspondence series (2.5 feet) is arranged both alphabetically (in two separate groups) and chronologically. The subseries arranged alphabetically covers the period of 1944 to 1964; the subseries arranged chronologically covers scattered years (1944-1945, 1948, and 1968-1972). Included are personal letters and professional memoranda documenting Axelrod's thoughts and his humane concern for his profession and clients. The second alphabetical sub-series exemplifies Axelrod's research interest in the late 1960s and details the growth and development of the Department of Medical Care Organization that Axelrod chaired during this time period.
  - Alphabetical, Group A, 1944-1964
    - A-D (Box 14)
    - E-J (Box 14)
    - Falk, Dr. Leslie, 1947-1961 (Box 14)
    - K-Sc (Box 14)
    - Kerr, Dr. Lorin, 1944-1957 (Box 14)
    - Koplin, Dr. Allen, 1945-1950 (Box 14)
    - Mott, Dr. F.D., 1946-1957 (Box 14)
    - Myers, Beverlee A (California Department of Health Services), 1980-1981 (Box 14)
    - Norwick, Dr. Sydney, 1945-1949 (Box 14)
    - Roemer, Dr. Milton, 1948-1961 (Box 14)
    - Se-Z and Unknown (Box 14)
    - Sheps, Dr. Cecil, 1948-1950; 1964 (Box 15)
    - Sigerist, Dr. Henry, 1947-1951 (Box 15)
    - Silver, Dr. George, undated; 1946-1959 (Box 15)
    - Terris, Dr. Milton 1949-1957, 1975 (New York Medical College), 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Weinerman, Dr. Richard, 1947-1958 (Box 15)
  - Chronological, 1944-1947; 1968-1986; 11 folders (Box 15)
  - Alphabetical, Group B, 1962-1975
    - Jaffe-Justis (Box 15)
    - Kahn-Kehoe (Box 15)
    - Kellog-Klarman (Box 15)
    - Klieger-Knoll (Box 15)
    - Koch-Kornbluh (Box 15)
    - Kost-Kurlander (Box 15)
    - Kerr, Lorin E., 1965-1972 (Box 15)
    - Koetting, Felix A., 1966-1967 (Box 15)
    - Koplin, Allen W., 1966-1969 (Box 15)
    - Krughoff, Merril F., 1968-1970 (Box 15)
    - Laird-Lashof (Box 15)
    - LaSure-Lehmann (Box 15)
    - LeMerc-Lewis (Box 15)
    - Lievow-Lipscomb (Box 15)
    - Logan-Loth (Box 16)
    - Lovelace-Lowinger (Box 16)
    - Luchi-Lurie (Box 16)
    - Lee, Philip R. Dr., 1962-1966; 1968-1969; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Locey, Robert Dr., 1969-1973 (Box 16)
    - Lyford, Marjorie, 1969 (Box 16)
    - McAuley-McCutchan (Box 16)
    - McGarvey-McNattin (Box 16)
    - Madison-Manegold (Box 16)
    - Mann-Mason (Box 16)
    - Martz-Meyer (Box 16)
    - Miller-Mott (Box 16)
    - Mueller-Myers (Box 16)
    - McNamara, Michael J., Dr., 1972-1974 (Box 16)
    - McNerney, Walter J., 1963-1967 (Box 16)
    - Mattison, Berwyn F., Dr., 1964-1969; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Mott, F. D., Dr., 1964-1971; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Mulder, Carel E. H., 1964-1971 (Box 16)
    - Mushkin, Selma J., 1972-1975 (Box 16)
    - Myers, Beverlee A., 1964-1971 (Box 16)
    - Mytinger, Robert E., Dr., 1966-1968 (Box 16)
    - Nash-Norwick (Box 16)
    - Notkin, Herbert, Dr., 1964-1970 (Box 16)
    - Obrinsky-Ostfeld (Box 16)
    - Palmer-Pepper (Box 16)
    - Perretz-Phaneuf (Box 16)
    - Pickett-Poole (Box 16)
    - Popick-Pyke (Box 16)
    - Rabin-Remington (Box 16)
    - Reinstein-Rice (Box 16)
    - Robbins-Rohrer (Box 16)
    - Romani-Rudich (Box 16)
    - Reader, George G., Dr., 1964-1973 (Box 16)
    - Reuther, Walter P., 1964-1968 (Box 16)
    - Roemer, Milton I., Dr., 1964-1972; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Saaco-Sbarbaro (Box 16)
    - Schike-Scutchfield (Box 16)
    - Shain-Sherman (Box 16)
    - Shorr-Shuval (Box 16)
    - Sibery-Sleight (Box 16)
    - Smith-Sondag (Box 16)
    - Sparer-Squires (Box 16)
    - Stanton-Stewart (Box 16)
    - Stoeffler-Swift (Box 16)
    - Saltzstein, Harry C., Dr., 1963-1973 (Box 16)
    - Segadelli, Louis J., 1964-1973 (Box 16)
    - Sheps, Cecil G., Dr., 1963-1973; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Shoemaker, Richard E. (AFL-CIO), 1966-1969 (Box 16)
    - Shore, Jerome, 1966 (Box 16)
    - Silver, George A., Dr., 1964-1973; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Sinai, Nathan Dr., 1963-1969; 1974-1975; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Stamler, Jeremiah, Dr., 1965-1975 (Box 16)
    - Strauss, Janet A., 1972-1975 (Box 16)
- Farm Labor Health Program
  The Farm Labor Health Program series (2.5 feet) centers around Dr. Axelrod's involvement in the Farm Labor Health Program as a commissioned employee of the United States Public Health office. His official position was Chief Medical Officer of the Migrant Health Project. The program was developed to investigate and improve the plight of migrant farm workers. This series extensively chronicles numerous aspects of the program including but not limited to: Budgets, Child Health, Clinical Equipment, Conferences, Health Services, Housing, Legislation, Medical Care, Migration Patterns, Sanitation and Individual State Programs.
  - Aging, 1945-1961 (Box 16)
  - Agricultural Workers Health Association, 1945
    - Child Health, 1943-1945 (Box 17)
    - Costs, 1941-1946 (Box 17)
    - Clinic Equipment, 1940 (Box 17)
    - Clinic Manual, 1945 (Box 17)
    - Dental Health, 1942-1948 (Box 17)
    - Field Handbook, 1945 (Box 17)
    - Field Handbook (Portland, Oregon), 1945 (Box 17)
    - Health Services (Local Programs), 1938-1946 (Box 17)
    - Legislation, 1946-1948 (Box 17)
    - Nursery Schools, 1946 (Box 17)
    - Testimony on H.R. 3367 (Health Problems of Migrant Workers), 1947 (Box 17)
  - Atlantic Seaboard Agricultural Workers Health Association, 1945
    - Health Association Handbook, 1947 (Box 17)
  - Budgets, 1945-1947 (Box 17)
  - Capacity and Occupancy of Farm Labor Supply Centers, 1946-1947 (Box 17)
  - Conferences, 1940-1945 (Box 17)
  - Farm Labor Force, 1940-1946 (Box 17)
  - Farm Security Administration, 1942-1943 (Box 17)
  - Federal Interagency Committee On Migrant Labor / Official Report on Proceedings, 1946 (Box 17)
  - Foreign Workers, 1946 (Box 17)
  - Health Services Procedure, 1944-1945 (Box 17)
  - Housing (General), 1941-1947 (Box 17)
  - Housing Survey (Beet Workers), 1942 (Box 17)
  - Immigration Trends and Movements, 1947 (Box 17)
  - Israel, 1942 (Box 18)
  - Labor Branch (USDA), 1946-1947 (Box 18)
  - Medical Care, 1939-1949 (Box 18)
  - Mexican Workers, 1942-1947 (Box 18)
  - Midwestern Agricultural Workers Health Association, 1946 (Box 18)
  - "Migrant Labor: A Human Problem,", 1947 (Box 18)
  - Migration Into the States of the Northwest, 1940 (Box 18)
  - Migratory Labor Health Association Reports, 1947-1948
    - Reports, 1946 (Box 18)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1936-1946 (Box 18)
  - Northeastern Division Labor Ranch ("Key to Health Services"), 1946 (Box 18)
  - Northwest Division Training Conference, 1946 (Box 18)
  - Nursing Migrants, 1942-1946 (Box 18)
  - Organization and Administration, 1945; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Patterns of Migration, 1947 (Box 18)
  - Physical Examination Forms, 1947 (Box 18)
  - Recommendations on the Education of Children of Migrant Workers, 1947 (Box 18)
  - Regulation of Migrant Labor Camps, 1946 (Box 18)
  - Report On Operations of the Farm Labor Health Program, 1943; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Residence Requirements for Public Assistance, 1946 (Box 18)
  - Sanitation Material (USDA), 1943-1946 (Box 18)
  - "Second Annual Report of the Chief Liaison Officer British West Indies Central Labour Organisation,", 1946-1947 (Box 18)
  - State Commission of Inquiry (Michigan), 1933 (Box 18)
  - State Extension Information, 1943-1947 (Box 18)
  - State Labor Laws Applicable to Agricultural Workers, 1946 (Box 18)
  - State Programs
    - Arizona, 1946-1950
      - "A Survey of the Migratory Agricultural Labor Population,", 1939 (Box 18)
    - California Correspondence, 1938-1947
      - Publications, 1937-1947 (Box 18)
    - Colorado, 1944-1948 (Box 18)
    - Connecticut, 1945 (Box 18)
    - District of Columbia, 1947 (Box 18)
    - Florida, 1940-1947 (Box 18)
    - Idaho, 1947 (Box 18)
    - Indiana, 1946 (Box 18)
    - Maine, 1946 (Box 18)
    - Mary, 1946-1947 (Box 18)
    - Montana (Box 18)
    - North Dakota, 1947 (Box 18)
    - New Jersey, 1940-1945 (Box 18)
    - North Carolina, 1948 (Box 18)
    - Puerto Rico, 1947-1950 (Box 19)
    - South Carolina, 1940s (Box 19)
    - Texas, 1947 (Box 19)
    - Utah, 1947 (Box 19)
    - Virginia, 1947 (Box 19)
    - West Virginia, 1940 (Box 19)
  - States Miscellaneous, 1947 (Box 19)
  - State Sanitation, 1941-1944 (Box 19)
  - State Sanitation Regulations, 1941-1944 (Box 19)
  - Statistics, 1943-1947 (Box 19)
  - Sugar Beet Workers, 1934-1946 (Box 19)
  - United States Department of Labor, 1946-1947 (Box 19)
  - United States Employment Service, 1948 (Box 19)
  - Wages of Agricultural Labor in the United States, 1946-1947 (Box 19)
  - Working Women, 1942-1943 (Box 19)
- Audio Materials, 1972; 1976
  Audio Materials (1 foot) consists of over sixty audio cassette tapes of Axelrod's classroom lectures on health insurance and medical care organizations.
  - Health Insurance Lectures, February-April 1972; 11 audiocassettes (Box 20)
  - Medical Care Organizations 600 Class Lectures, September-December 1976; 50 audiocassettes (Box 20)